Everybody my name's rob howard a program manager on the
offs extensibility team and today we're going to get our hands dirty with the office three sixty
five api is a word of warning...will be and exhausting session
I'll I will be exhausted afterwards or go-fast them to cover a ton of stuff I'm going to
go through a bunch of stuff...protocol level detail so if you're not quite prepared for that if you will
...session you may want to find a different one for the our but,
with that let's go and get started for everybody who's reduce the along fluoride.
Please submit evaluation afterwards
the gennifer today we're going to start off with a really brief little bit on why you should integrate with the office
three sixty-five api is...you should bring office we sixty-five into your app
they're going to get started on how to do that...to go into a lot of detail about the first step which is
integrating single sign on so letting people sign into your application...i-device app or
web app with our office three sixty five identity and the next step with xyz taking
...office three sixty five api is and bringing them into your application to make it smarter to take the
users schedule or their files...one drive-in let them pull it directly into your
application so they don't have to...their service yourselfand,
then the last is for those first two things were going to focus
...on the protocol level details and exactly how stuff works under the covers in the nitty-gritty
rest the different the tokens you need the exchanges between
...directory and office three sixty five but there's a ton of tools and sdk
is and I'll show you a bunch of those...can focus on so that well after the session you'll be a great expert
and how all that stuff works hopefully...day-to-day you won't have to use
it you actually just be able to use these tools to be much more productive and efficient integrating them so,
you've probably seen this slide before if you want to...jeremy's
...just to give you a quick overview of for the office platform we kind of think of...is being
too big aspects and one is this user...notion that users
are inside office getting things done and we want you to
...developers to be able to create custom experiences that extend office with
your own services with your own capabilities there's a bunch of talks on that...as a talk
I believe right after this one on all the capabilities we have for extending office and all of its many different forms
of many different platforms the second piece of it is the ability to connect office three
sixty-five data into from whatever application your building whether that's a device
application or a service application or even a web page connect office three
sixty five data and make your apps richer and this is we're going to focus on this session that second
piece the office we sixty-five api is that let you get to that data from wherever
you're building your application you've probably seen the school before or something like if you
...anybody from the office...over platform team talk we're very happy about such as being
so this obviously we think it's very strategic for the company as well if you think about it for anybody who's
in office three sixty five user the identity that the use and office three sixty five is the one that they
use to get their job done every day so letting you use that as a
basis the identity your application and then letting you take things like
...calendar which is the canonical source of where they are and who they're meeting with
and what they're working on and the files in one drive which is the important projects that
they're working on...notes in one node and all the other places that we have an office
...the help people get work done and bringing that
...your application is what makes this such as strategic api for us?
...all starts with single sign on that's really the first step is to take
your application whatever form it is and let people sign into it with our office three sixty five accounts and
...to go get another use name and password or if they do so they can connect using password
directly to their office we sixty-five account and get both pieces of functionality and integrated way as
...active directory is the basis for all of these accounts obviously sixty-five actually uses
...directory and profile system.
All the users all the passwords that are native
...directory...inside of or the native to office...sixty-five users are inside
...active directory and...active directory is a vibrant identity platform in the...
sets your like eighty six percent of fortune five hundred companies are using these microsoft services that take advantage
of resurrected directory...more than five million organizations that use as
...directory to...denny's in the cloud have more than a billion
authentication the day so it's a really active and vibrant ecosystem for doing sign in
as part of an organization so if you want if you have a productivity app and you want people to be able to get work
done with your application allowing them to assigning with...kind of a no-brainer.
How does this work in the context of office...sixty-five we use as
...active directory as that single protocol to do the authentication even
for on apps but certainly for third-party applications for third-party applications
...first step is signing a user in and we typically recommend a really simple
flow that's become the web standard for doing sign in called open id connect it's a close
...protocol author...of the nitty-gritty details about hope
and open id connect works this is how you let a user sign in with
our office we sixty-five account resurrected director account into your application the next step is
once they've signed in you can ask the user to give you access to their services and office we
sixty-five on your behalf through...so you can do things like...to their directory to look at
...management hierarchy see who their direct reports are a stewart groups are member of
...condo exchange to get their calendar and see if there free are busy at this time rc what meetings
...or what location are coming from and going to
...more intelligent apps as result we've had some integration with
as director directory with exchange was sharepoint with one drive for business for a
little while we have new integration very recent and I'll talk about all the...run agree with the
amr and one node api as well so you can now use interactive directly to sign into those api
...and you can use it from any sort of application whether you're building a device application
we're building a web application we now support...and the odf implicit flown
to allow you to build single page apps so directly from html you can call these office three sixty-five api
...users and we also support service apps all the office we sixty-five api
measure active directory now support app authentication apple only...
credentials flow you can have a service application like a demon process that runs
...does say management operations on everybody'semail mailbox overnight or
does operations like provisioning that require hire user privileges and wouldnt be doable by an
end-user typically a and all this stuff is available whether you're connecting directly with a company
...administrator if you have an application your building that you sell
...it department and they acquire it they can give your app access to all of the
organizations content on behalf of all of its users all at once
throughout and consent or if you actually engage with end-users directly and uone
...end-user...organization to adopter out
they can individually consent access to their own services they can let you sign them in
...their ten admins approval of course tenements can decide they want to turn that feature off
but the vast majority of tenants do not of the feature off
and use can turn that on as well and it's all based on secure standard protocols
open id connector authentication for that single sign
...peace and o off to for access to those resourcesand,
this protocol has a ton of advantages I'm sure you're pretty familiar with but just to give
aac really quick recap it doesn't require
...application capture user credentials great that you don't have to type in
...the application and
your application doesn't have to try and store that securely and gives you fine-grain access so the app
...ask for exactly what it wants to access and only gets access to adjuster
calendar not everything of access to so if you're ten administrator can't suddenly start
leaving your directory or something like that just because you happen to start using this application
a and supports a bunch of offload...users that are really important for organizations
in the enterprise so multi factor authentication and federated sign
...on premises identity providers all that stuff is kind of...transparently as
parties protocols as you'll see in just a minute then it gives you long-term accesses api is if
...user hasn't revoke your apps access you can use a
refresh token to access their services on their behalf even when they're
not interactively using your app and do smart for smart things for them while they're asleep send them summary
emails send them intelligent things based on changes in their data so, you've got a ton of features here for how
...directory ads a ton of value when you're interacting with office we sixty-five api
So, I'm actually going to do is go through the details of the protocol flow we're going to
go through how open id connect and off work in the context
...directory...office we sixty-five...diagram and I'm actually going to go
through by hand...this is a quick flow diagram on the left-hand side you'll see
your application on the right-hand side there's an office...sixty-five api want to call so you want to get
a users exchange calendar the middle there's a couple of endpoints in as
you're active directory the authorization endpoint...the token...we use a pretty typical author
...connect flow in order to do this so first thing application does is
it requests on authorization code from that authorization and point inside
...directory and the other...employee you can kind of think of as a web page is a
web page that the app is going to send the user to either
in a browser window or through a browser redirect or it's going to use a web browser control in
a native app is going to send the user to that authorization endpoint
web page and that's where you see that prototypical off-screen that says hey you want to give the app
access to this stuff you want to let it access your mail you want to let it reader files
a and the at...user gets an opportunity to say yes or no the user says yes
the authorization endpoint returns what's called...authorization code to your application
...authorization code signifies...app has given your app access
to the user has given europe access to that stuff.
The application...around and makes a web service call to the token endpoint
...sends that authorization code...up the user gave me access of this stuff and the token endpoints web
service returns a bunch of tokens returns...id token
and access token and a refresh token and if you're doing just single sign on
an open id connect...token is where you can stop that I d token has
...identity it'll give you profile information if you've got permission to get their name you can
tell and hello rob you now sign in with your account we've got your user profile
...we now understand who you are if you want to continue in access services on their behalf when
you take that access token and...that access token to call the office
three sixty-five api just like you would any other web service api
so a pretty simple straightforward offload...connect flow let's actually go and see
...action so I'm going to go through and we're going to do the whole thing from scratch without
any libraries without any code we're just going to do it in the browser
and with a bunch of kind of tool so you can see the request back and forth.
This is exhausting for you ready.
Okay,
so, actually going to start in office we sixty-five this is the admin portal if you haven't seen it
of reason I start here is because I am...administrator and office we sixty-five tenant
it's very creatively called robs developer tenant remember the name it's hard
to remember a and robs developer tenant is an office
we sixty-five tenant but when I created it under the covers we created measure active directory
...to store all of its users in groups and applications as you'll see if I go,
for example, to this...I look at the active...you can
see list of users you can see groups here and this allows me
...create manage the groups inside of my portal and, you also see
listing here down to a link to adjective directories management portal
...switch over to that management portal you can see a directory name the same thing as that office
three sixty five organization robs developer tenet and you can see if I go to the user tab, for example,
that you'll see the exact same list of users that were in the office them so if I create a
user here you'll see in office of...create a user and office you'll see it here same for groups
a so this is really the underlying directory for office even though as an office
and you may not actually interact with a very often if I want to manage applications
on experience for that in the office of in portal to go to the...
active directory portal and go to the applications tab when you start when you first
...in here with an office we sixty-five...you're probably just see a couple of apps in here
if filter for office we sixty-five you can see office
...sixty-five exchange online and office three sixty five sharepoint online those are probably
be the only to you may have a couple more depending on what you've done...you can see that are actually published by microsoft
corporation these are the core apps that model sharepoint in exchange for off purposes
...all the same way...will be you can see is an admin I get to manage not only the apps that
I'm creating my organization but any apps that have access to data
inside of my organization or that are being used inside of my...if I want to create a new one
just go to add can choose to add something from a gallery that somebody
else is produced but I'm actually at one of my organization is creating...to call
...demo twenty fifteen I can choose whether I want to do a web
application or native client application choose web application...requires a couple more...I get to explain
all more there's the sign on url which is a pretty simple straightforward thing I'm creating
a web application this is...the url we're going to sign in so I'm just going to do http
gone slash made up website I used actually say that may...website
...register domain but then I actually gave its okwesa that and somebody in the audience during my talk one
registered the domain so it's actually register now we're still no real website there so
you sears we go...but that's okay a and as I...is app id uri which this one's a little unfortunate
...you're active directory supports a ton of different protocols like
...and several p and a whole bunch of things that are much more complicated than often
...and authors and actually use this but,
for right now we still ask you for it so policies about that we'll get that fixed very soon but,
the strategy to use here is you need a unique ui and you need one that's a
register domain so
...I created this office...sixty-five ten I called it junction the user names are like junction
...microsoft-dot-com going to use that as the domain so they get
a register domain and then I'm just going to put something unique afterwards it doesn't really matter I'm actually going to
users for off...I'm going to verify that this is actually unique first.
Surely that's unique.
Hopefully I didn't lose internet.
...can impending.
There...try and change it.
All right so complete so created this application it's going to go
...provision a new application inside of my directory.
Come on, network and even on the wired network.
We'll see when this comes up is...have a configuration
tabs so I can look at all the properties my application I can see things like...name for the application
assign on url I can see a logo for that I can replace.
I can configure all that stuff from inside...directory open another...in case.
Very ok so...the configure tab you can see build demo twenty fifteen as
the name you can see that sign on url you can see the logo that we can replace I can configure whether
or not the application is multi tenet...leave that as no for right now but I'm actually going to have to come back
...just a minute I'll explain in more detail you can see clients id this is sort of like the user
name for the application so that uniquely identifies my application along the protocol
...you can see keys this is kind of like a password from application and ask
the create a new one it won't show which means I had save which is a little bit annoying but
I can deal with it the next thing I'll see is that by
the uri we already talked about and then the reply url and the reply url is if you think back
...diagram...to the authorization endpoint the user said yes I want to give you stuff and we sent
back and off code enough that authorization code
reply url is where we're going to send that authorization code so I'm going
to keep this is made up website dot com I could put a path behind...if I want to specific page on meta website dot
com but the website is made up so it doesn't exist...have a path so we'll just leave it
is that a and then the most interesting thing down here is permissions to other applications and this is
where I say that my app wants to do single sign on that once access to...business that
wants access to exchange online...and I do that by defaultmy permissions
our to windows...directory just to do single sign on and read the user's profile so basically
just to do that open id connect part but I can also add applications and you'll see a bunch of
applications from microsoft here you can see exchange online you can see sharepoint online you can
cone note now you can see our bytheir bunch more that you'll see depending
...being used in your tenant you can even create custom applications
and exposure permissions that way so there's not just microsoft applications for now logistic
...sharepoint online exchange online for each one of those you
can configure the delegated permissions user permissions that you want to ask users for so I
want to say, for example, a I want to be able to read and write contacts or read and write calendars or send
mails user reading...user
...there's a bunch...in their around running searches reading and writing their files and
wonder for business we have a bunch of new scopes that
actually just ship this week for a bunch of sharepoint workloads like management...and user profiles
and search...you can add those as well so those are the delegated permissions also explain
...quick the application permissions application permissions or for those service application
scenarios I was talking about where I have ca demon app that runs on a regular basis and
does maintenance tasks are goes and does provisioning or does smart things in the middle-of-the-night for all the users in
organization
a and these aren't on behalf of particular user they're not delegated by user they
are application permissions that are called directly by the application so I can also give applications permission
that way and exchange and sharepoint measure active directory all now support that right so
...configure my permissions or go ahead and it...
It's...a second ago and create that...creating that I'll show you this dialog here if you click
view endpoints in the bottom you get this handy dialogue...shows you a bunch of different protocol
I'm points you stuff like...fed and sample p and a bunch of really complicated
protocols...bottom you'll see two things that hopefully sound familiar off to authorization endpoint and off
to token endpoint so, you saw those two lines in the first diagram I can take
those and I can use those as the basis for my protocol flume one thing you'll see here is that
in the urls they actually have a guid is the second segment for the url that's
the tenant url this eight nine...ad for thing that's the
tenant url I actually a little scratched right here where I have authorization...point in the
token endpoint instead of the guid I'm using common and common works for
all multi ten application so if I create...app in my robs developer tenant and I want somebody
...different tend to use it I can use the common and...across all of them.
All right so this is essentially the same thing I've got authorization
...commons...go off to slash authorizes the authorization
...it's got a redirect...which is again the place where...want to send the authorization code
a response type which tells...what I want back in this case I want to code back there also some flows
...can ask for token directly if you're doing a web page app a and then I have to tell which clients
idea...to take that from the...the just saved.
Copy the client id and come back here and pasted in and then I'm just going to copy and
paste that into a browser window because remember I said hey this is just a web page authorization
...just a web page.
I'm going to encode media window so I'm actually not signed in I actually am signed in
bummer.
Me closing coordinator windows.
Try that again.
Who not...ok so I'm not sign...it's going to force me to sign in
first and, I'm actually going to sign in with the user from a different tenant and in fact I'm
...with my actual microsoft-dot-com account so this is my real microsoft the
...for work every day...with it for two reasons one because it's in a different
...from the one...register the app...issue about looks like...because
msit does this thing that I consider really sadistic annoying which is they require a bunch of extra off
...I go and sign in a so if I move out of your seo recognizesthis
tenet requires a whole bunch of extra sign in so they're going to redirect
...and I have to sign in this is an on premise eighty of us that msit hose
...sign in with a smart card or if I do a username
and password like this it's going to tell me a so you actually have to have some
extra security information and hopefully it's going to call my phone?
And, then when...my phone after type in a pin in order to finish the authentication
forget reception here?
Area hey it's ringing on certain
...usually don't answer phone calls during my social
...an exception okay so...my pin there.
The authentication continues and,
then...error but years...so I am actually signed in
...the app actually had no idea that all that other stuff happen all the...redirect all the
...stuff all that stuff was my it department configured it as an app develop
...have to do anything to handler so it's one of the great things about often open id connect is
all that interstitial introduction of all stuff is totally free.
I didn't get an error though I did...purpose I'll show you a couple of things with this
...one is that if you try this at home all the copying and pasting and taking
...from here there you're almost certainly to mess up at least once a I
will mess up at least once during this demo I'm sure...get an error and the first
error that you see up here is an end-user facing...and it's not very helpful it says sorry were having trouble saying
...we received a bad request so it doesn't like the authorization
endpoint requests I made look down here instead this is the developer facing
...and this little light great taxed it says application
with identifier and that guid is the client id for the new app I created
was not found in the directory and this grid is the grid for the microsoft it
tenet was telling me I can't find the app that you're trying to sign in within your...
Multichannel so in when I went back here.
I can find the page again one here remember I said application is not multi tenant
...the app in my robs...and I try...be used in microsoft tenant
...said is not multi tenants...yes and...save to make it multi tenant this
is a good time to tell you that the adjective directory...eventually consistent model for the directory so
when you make a change can sometimes take like fifteen twenty seconds...you're doing a demo
...going to tap dance for a little bit well the whole thing propagates and then we get to make the changes
...some point you can say okay well it probably is
...exchanging but if you're doing this and you actually...problem and you try it and make a change
...doesn't take effect just wait fifteen seconds and try again and, check and see
...to do this again this time...has we sign then so...should be pretty quick.
And, hopefully all the changes to make...tenant have propagated.
Great so now I'm at the actual authorization endpoint this is that consent experience
were talking about I can see that title my application build demo twenty fifteen I can see the url where
the applications registered made up website dot com I can see the exact...permissions
...application is asking for those are all the boxes that I checked out the end user can
mouse over these boxes to get a little bit more details on what that means I can see who I'm
sign in as...even more details I can see which organization I'm a part of
an which organization publish this application that's asking from all this stuff and say well
robs development and...guy sounds really shady I don't really want to give them access and cancel
or are...I'm going to in this case...say that...a stand-up guy and I'm
ahead except first I'm actually going to go over to a tool how many people use fiddler?
Awesome almost everybody grades so fiddler for the few people
...use that is a web debugging tool it's spectacular for looking at requests across the wire
...started capturingbefore I make this except request and I'm going
to hit except a and remember what's going to happen it's going to create and offload and it's going to
...to made up website dot com so it looks like a this is a blank website that has
...register anything I'm going-to go-to for the real quick and stopper capturing the one thing I'll
point out though is that if you actually look in the query string made up website dot com but you'll see
this parameter code equals and that's that authorization code this is the thing that says
...the user just said you can access my office we sixty-five api is
what authorization code is what I'm going to use...then called the token endpoint right so I'm actually do that
...back in a fiddler again I can see the request
...that made up website dot com request here's the code I can look at the so for those
...these are all the requests that happened while I was in there on the right-hand
side agency inspectors all kinds of different views on the request and I can see, for example,
the web forms parameters that were
sent here's the query string parameter code and its value so I can see that code also sends
a session state which you can actually round-trip if you send somebody to the authorization and point you can
set...state and they'll send it back to you so you can keep track and correlate those
requests if you need to I've got this request...go ahead and remove all the on all of the
...other sessions in their a anomaly make requests
...token endpoint to go and get that access token so I've got the token
endpoint here again the...is bree similarly named instead of common or
through such authorizes common or to slash token when a copy that guy
...another feature filler called the composer which lets me create new web trafficand,
I'm actually going to...in.
This url for the token endpoint going to get rid of all
the headers there I'm going to make a post request instead of a get request...I've actually got a post a
bunch of information about the stuff I have to redeem this token.
I'm going to take this.
Placeholder text and show you all the information that I have to sense
...left the first thing I have to say is what type of proof
in my showing you that a user gave me a grant the user granted me consent so grant type
...the first thing in this case I'm going to give it that authorization codes...say authorization code
after...the redirect...just to make sure that the redirect
your code was sent to the right uri and that everything matches up from a security perspective I have to give it the
client id to so which client...go back here.
And, copy that guy.
And,...the n.
And,...I have to go give the client secret one unfortunate thing about the client secret is
it's not always url safe it's always url encoded
...you got to do a quick encoding actually one thing I learned preparing for this is that if you just search for url
encoder on bing actually gives you an inline url encoder...not cool.
Saw encode this thing grab it can go back to
...and pace that in as the client secret and then I need that code so go
back to inspector and copy the code.
And, pace that guy and then the last thing I need is the resource
and the resources a little bit special...darker and office we sixty-five that you won't find this in like
a single service offload like if you're only talking a facebook you don't have the
...resource...this case we have a bunch of different services that we're talking to
want to end-user to only cone consent screen...one-off code one
refresh token we actually have to get different access tokens for the different services want-to talk to-you
so-if the tell which service I want to go talk to I do that by basically putting a uri
and here so,
in this case I'm going to start with a service called the discovery service which I'll talk about just a minute
it's on api our office dot com slash discovery
...use that as my resource whether anything right I'm ahead execute?
...a two hundred response back here and if I look at the
response I get back a bunch of json...look at the json version of the response I can see a
little bit cleaner fashion the first I'll talk about is the id token the aidid token is if
you're doing just doing as a so if you're just doing open id connect this is all you need you describe the
aidid token you can check the expiration things like that but you grab the id token and you use
that to sign the user...token is what's called a...token which is how you cj
...json web token...one of the only...that I know that like the first sentence of the
...says you pronounce this...guess they're just really didn't want to have like the gift
version jeff controversies so it's just not swat so I take this gw t token
...token is a...the foreign coded json string?
So, if I take this thing and I go and on encode it and,
there happens to be this handy little draught viewer caleb be dot
...pace that guy n and
...remove this id token equals thing from the front they will
...encode this thing and you'll see inside of it json so very simple
json like you get back from any other web service that tells me all about who that user is just
...point out a couple of parameters and caleb be
net actually will show you all the meaning behind these parameters to if you mouse over them so cool resource
of audiences the application is tokens intended force is actually the same client
idea I got back from the measure management portal this is the tenant id that the users from so this is a microsoft
ten-ninety this is the object id that identifies the user hears my user principle name
are howard...my given name rob and my family name which is howard
...actually like a bunch of
rob howard's at microsoft it's really annoying so I have the specify officeand,
then you can actually see one other thing that's really cool which is that if I actually have an application that
...how strong the sign-in was this amr thing is
the authentication methods reference...a json array of all the methods that were used authenticate
...so I can cp wd for password and mf a for multi factor off so I can see that
...user sign in with both of those if I want to do some extra
authorization say this is a super privilege operation have to be sign in with fa or something all right and,
I'm done if I'm doing open id connect right I just take the username take the display name and
...got my application ready to go...open id connect stops
Just continues on from there we're going to go through that real quick so
...it uses all the other parameters in here the access token in the refresh...
in particular and the access token is again the token I take as my app and I send over
that office we sixty-five api to make a web service call so first...to make as the discovery service and I'm
going to copy this access token go back to the composer I'm going to make a get requests
...all this other stuff.
I'm...to make that get request the discovery service which is that https.
...slash api dot office dot com slash discovery.
And, I want to get
wvu on slash me and all of my services and what this
endpoint is going to do...going to give me back all of the services that this user
has the this token gives you access to
...back all the endpoints all the descriptions of them so things you might have had to do in the past where
you do things like ask the user where sharepoint site is or where one driver business
site is you don't have to do that anymore because this discovery services a static url and
...give you a pointer to all those but I have to give it the access token that I just got
...the way I do that is an header called authorization I type in the
string bearer as in this is a bearer token and I give a space and then I just
...in the access token
...at home there's this really annoying thing which is every time you copy of the json viewer it will give you the name to
...to delete access underscore token equals a and I just
execute and I get a request back from...office dot com and what you'll see
in here is a bunch of different entries for all the different services that this access token gave me access
to see capability my files you'll see the service endpoint url as on microsoft
...my...sharepoint dot...knows me so my application can discover these...runtime
and doesn't have to know or microsoft tenants here or composers...here...get all
this stuff at runtime you can see the service and point you are you can see the resource id balance
from my files here's one for contacts here's one for mail?
Here's one for calendar of ask for other services like your directory hierarchy then...get one for
...directory things like that so discovery services probably
your first stop when you're building a new...signing user in for the first-time to find out world
their services but actually want to interact with their services in order to go get their data in order
to go interact with their calendar, for example,
so, I will instead go back and get a new token remember I have to have
...an access token that specific to each service of this somehow
have to ask user for anything I can use the refresh token to go get a new access
token without asking the user for anything I'm going to start from this token request and I'm going to
do another feature called replay re issue from composer which just takes that
request and dumps in the composer...I'm going to make just a little change here
which is that instead of grants I because authorization code I want refresh token.
A and instead of the actual code.
I want.
To give the refresh tokenso, I can get that from this response
refresh token equals and just...that right where the code was the last thing I want
to do is change the resource to point towards the resource,
resource id for my calendar was outlook the office
three sixty-five dot com so that
in a execute again now I'm getting a new access token you can see the access
token here without asking the user for a new one and I can do that for as long as the
refresh token is good which is a rolling window of six months so
...the user is continue using your application you
can continue to act on their behalf until they say I don't like your app anymore and revoke
its permission so I think this access token now and start making some calls into office
we sixty-five...and this is the sort
of portion when I'm switching from hey we did all the often open id connect stuff now I'm going
to do a bunch of api stuff but I'm again going to do it at the rest layer I'm just going to show you the
...directly so I'm going to start off with some basic ones I'm going to do a get requestand,
I'm going to make it to.
Outlook dot office we sixty-five dot com which is again where the counter services
a slash api...I'm going to make the most basic request I can think of
which is just give me the information about the current user so slash me and
I'll do authentication authorization bearer.
And, pace that and again get rid of the actual still going again.
...execute and...exchanges going to return to me some
really basic information about the user just through the current user is what...mailbox...
it is so I have success I have now called my first office we sixty-five api
and exchange obviously that's kind of a lame one or do some more interesting one so mccall slash
events me slash events and this is going to give me all of the events on the users default
...so if I go inside of inspectors you'll see I've
actually some really simple clean json to get all of the events on the...so you can see
...event on my calendar here you can see its location here's the display
...and the conference room you can see the list of attendees
...their email addresses...you can see the start time and the
end-time the start time and the subject and
...so really simple straightforward json the described my calendar I'm in
an unbounded request so I just ask for all of the events on my calendar so
...thing you'll see that's also comment all the office...sixty-five api is that if
we decide hey there's we can give you all the data and one-page you'll see this
...data dot next link parameter at the top which says there's another page of this data and
you can continue grabbing more pages if you'd like the rest of the data from the service and all the office
...sixty-five api behave in that same way so you can count on that same behavior for paging if I want to
go in here and I want to limit the amount of objects that I get back I can just say I only want
to top to dollar top equals two and the query string again all the office
we sixty-five api have the same behavior if I had execute you'll
...only get back to objects in the response instead of the many objects that I got
back the other parameters like say I don't really care about all of the metadata there
was a lot of stuff in...maybe I only care about a few things so
I can do a dollar select and I can say just give me
back the id the subject?
The start and the location...this will actually
then limit the response to only return all of those fields so
you see id location start...subject for the two objects that were there so now
I've limited bites over the wire made it really efficient...the api limited
the parsing I have to do to pull it back in...and you see those two stack so I have my
...my dollar top and my dollar select...both as parameters that...going to
back and I have the selector I can do some more things like that so, for example, a
say I wanted-to get back only specific objects by filtering them
so I can do dollar filter and there's a little many filter language that does all kinds of stuff
like equals greater than less than contains starts with
...and I'm going to just...do a simple one rama say filter where the subject
I have to encode this eq for equals and,
I'll just say.
Soccer game.
I'm a lover of soccer so I have a few these on my calendar and all
...execute there's well...one as the parser a little bit more stuff so it takes a little bit
more time but then you see I get back just appointments that include the
have a subject of soccer game and then the last one I'll show you is for this thing is
...can also order those so if you look at this request a I have a
soccer game from like last week or actually from monday...a soccer game from
twenty-nine I actually like them in chronological order so I'll go back to the composer.
I clicked and inspector that's going to crash no.
Question fingers everybody hold your breath.
So, what I'm going to do in this comes back is I'm going to go back to composer and I'm going
to add dollar order by to the query string parameter...I'm just going to say dollar order by
equal start and then it will order all the responses by that start field and I can do a common
delimited list of our or by multiple and I can specify whether I want them to be ascending
or descending again...back okay so I'll go back here and do?
Dollar order.
By equals start and,
it execute...and then you'll see I get back actually a game from
twenty-seven again from twenty-nine in the order that they were on my calendar so,
all of those things all those query string parameters is one of the nice consistent things about all these office
we sixty-five api if they support that functionality they supported through those same mechanisms
...or filter dollar order by dollar top use off the same way you access
...access tokens the same way that
functionally works across a variety of services just a couple of
other real quick things I'll show you so these services aren't just for reading data are
also for writing data so I'm actually going to go and show you my calendar real quick.
Someone login obviously sixty-five.
I'm going to switch over.
Switch over my calendar.
you can see today so we're on wednesday april nineteenth for those you
are familiar aren't familiar with our rest api typically work I've been doing a bunch of get requests on
the events collectionso, get on me slash events and
...get request on events usually means say get me all the things that are in the events collection
...another should be verb called post if you post to a collection...usually means
add another item to this collection so if I want to add a new event
...I would typically do it by doing a post events after-thought what type of content amount of
post sources a megabyte just some simple json and,
then adding to is really simple so I just create a json body or do subject?
And, I'll do start.
Of the type this...utc so let's
...my date math is okay you guys can check me
...and minus eight so.
We're in sixteen.
Yeah, good call start thanks
and user good you're really paying attention thank you.
So, somebody somewhere close to this time I think it's a little earlier ...and I'll do
...just an hour later...twenty-nine...
Twenty-three fifty-five since I don't think...let me do twenty-four.
Okay,
and, then I'll just sit execute...of a format everything right I should get back
to a one which is a shun figure http response for created a and
then I should see.
On this calendar.
In just a moment a new appointment called test show up...did all the
...math right.
So, there's my testappointment so obviously I can do reads I can do
rights...with a whole bunch of very robust functionality...go back real quick to the
slides and...a lot of demo hopefully they gave you a good solid idea what's going on
behind the scenes what's going on in the protocols just a quick review of the stuff you
saw the first part of discovering services using that discovery service again that's api
about office dot com slash discovery tells you where all the services you have access
art uses that same measure direct active directory authenticationyou saw the office
...sixty-five api is...simple restdata service api is
...a bunch of consistent behavior they authenticate the same way you use...same sort of
query string parameters they have the same sort of json encoding across them you can find all of their
urls to discovery and you can because they're just using standard
off and open id connect and rest you can use them from any sort
of application whether it's web advice on any platform or any sort of service application that...building
...a bunch of different pieces of functionality...sixty-five api is this isn't even
really super complete but this will give you a good summary and almost all of these on
the slide actually have a dedicated session this week to talk about them so if you want
to see the nitty-gritty details of any one of these particular ones got as ready
...stuff I think that one unfortunate was like last...quan did some stuff on
...exchange online of...going to do a session
on outlook dot com api is...counter contact there there's a bunch of
sessions on sharepoint listen libraries and searching user profile
...gregg in the back of the rooms doing something on friday about one drive-in
...for business they even have a conversion api that works the same for consumers and organizations to get
users files and folders...is doing one-on-one note a so
you can use the same audrey sixty-five api is to look at people's notes...their notebooks
the yam are has now support for...directory authentication the video portal api
...which is new kind of enterprise youtube thing for managing videos...set
...video api...an this new unify groups infrastructure which you may have started to hear about which is a
new collaboration infrastructure for collaborating across boundaries with a single group of people in office
...sixty-five also has a set of api...available through this unify
...point you may have heard about I'll talk about more...second if you want to know the nitty-gritty
details I definitely check out our office we sixty-five rest api reference I know in the past a bunch of
our rest api references been pretty crummy if you actually go and check this out it's pretty good
there's actually even some things where you can there's always room for us to improve I'm sure but if you go
and check it out you can actually look at the api
reference you can go and dive into specific api so say I want to
look at the outlook mail rest api a I can do things like look at all the different operations
supports I can click on one like get a message and I can see the urls I can
see sample requests even change parameters and say hey I want to look at the
inbox I can hit try and it will in the browser make requests to a sample tenet without
me even signing in and show you what the requesting response looks like so some pretty saw
...covers pretty much all of the office we sixty-five...guys that I have...so,
go back and show you that url again this is definitely the url...any to if you
want to look at the details of all the different office three sixty five api is that we support.
Okay, so,
I showed you I did the demo for the office research vibe api is one thing I want to talk about really quick there
are a few awkward things in that demo if like I had to go to the as...active directory portal register...application
or a bunch of non office...sixty or non author related things in there all of these
obviously sixty-five api...on different url you so like outlook that office we sixty-five dot...you saw
...might sharepoint dot com and api about discovery dot com I had to do like
an extra discovery step in order to get it and...to go get multiple different access tokens to act
with to interact with different services actually gets even a little bit more complicated if you say want
to go get the user that modified...file and then go to a different api to go find what department
their or who their manager is so those are kind of complicated scenarios when you cross the boundaries of these
...or actually announcing this week we've created this unify api you might have seen it
in...such as demo during the keynote
...graft microsoft common allows you to get to all these office three sixty five api...unify
...point exactly to address all those points so...have to deal with any of that stuff anymore
on this api it's still...preview will certainly continue invests and this and the messes are
want-to send is that it's really the same but simpler
...all of the app registrations of the permission...the open id to the open-eyed
...off to flows are all the same the simpler pieces that you get that one
...point you only have one access token you don't have to discovery but the api themselves are the
same and...is going to do a session tomorrow I think it's the second slot like maybe ten
thirty or something on the unify endpoint should go into a ton of detail so if you want to learn about unify
...of specifics there go and check it out it's really a very cool infrastructure that were really,
really excited about being the future these api is I've talked about this one quite a bit but this is just
...you can see we have a bunch of things that have already been...available
...launching a bunch of preview things right now on the unify them point the video poorly-paid
...one node at api is...api is a and work continuing iterate
...of things that will and soon things like having the same api for consumer properties
and commercial properties which...talk about for one drive and...we'll talk about for
our dot com we've got the office graphic api that gives you those insights
about documents that are interesting to you are people that work with other people across a boundaries
...tasks api coming we've got lincoln scape api is that are coming up we're going to
continue to iterate on these things and build more and more very quickly during
that time okay so next thing is tools and as the case
so I know that was a ton of work to go through all that but hopefully you guys really
deeply understand everything that happens in these author question these...requests...
The good news is that the vast majority of time you don't actually need to know that stuff it's
good to understand it's, you know, what's going on it's good to understand so
on something goes wrong you really aren't just using a library but, we've got tools and...case
...pretty much every platform that you can use in order to be more efficient
more productive than having to go through fiddler and getting access token for everyone of your customersso,
all-star with off because...is really the hardest peace and the piece where you want
to library the most and adjective...guys of
...awesome job of building a ton of libraries and...open-source libraries if you go to
...active directories at the adjective directory organs get...you
can see a ton of their client libraries that handles that entire offload for you don't have to mess with
off codes or access tokens or open id connect tokens are jobs
...no any that stuff in order to deal with the off pieces through these libraries
...really nice for building an application really quickly and I'll show you an example that in just a second
it's as you can see it there a ton of different platforms that are covered microsoft platforms and
on microsoft platforms that are cover there in terms of those libraries so definitely check those out and I'll show you an
example of those right now I'm going to go on build a really simple app and this is
going-to be you decidedly on the hey, there's nothing
sort of microsoft specific about these technologies in fact I'm actually going to start in sublime just
to show you there's no tricks...rice leave I'm just building a text application I've
got a html and javascript application this is really just a frame for an app it's
...angular apple...it looks like right now if I go here my node server
running.
If I go here and I run it.
It's basically just a frame for an app called
...course them with angular and...got a bunch of headings where I would like to have my calendar events my messages my
wonder for business files all that good stuff but they're not there because they don't have the code written
...go back in the app if you're not familiar with angular it's a really nice little framework for building
single page applications I've got a frame page called...html which
...and angular reference a...angular route reference it's got a reference
to adjective directories javascript library for doing all this all stuff
...javascript another library that they...that's really slick...integration between
eight-hour...angular so if you're building and angular app and you're doing...you should definitely check this thing...and,
then I've got my app
js which declares my app and creates a couple of dependencies here and then configures the routes
...user visits the root of the application I want to invoke this controller called home
...which is you can see down here is empty right now and,
I want to use this template home that html as
...html work-at-home that html that's where all those headings...
unscom and it's got a list right now that's just not being filled in by dynamic data so
...going to go and fill those in...see how easy it is compared to all the stuff we just in
...second so I've got a snippet.
I've got a snippet for doing the eight-hour
configured so this is the conflict that a library I have to tele which tenant this
app works against so I can create a single ten-to-one by giving a specific ten or I can say common
...excuse me for to work everywhere I think...the
...id that's just that same glad I got out of the adjective
...portal I can specify a bunch of extra parameters like if I want admin can sander
...always want a prompt or if I want in this case the new...instead of the old ux and,
then I have to give the endpoints...endpoints are just the endpoints that I would like as
you're active directory to automatically go get me an access token for an attach the
request yes it automatically goes and gets you in access token if you put them in here which is super cool
A sharepoint url and here you see outlook that office we sixty-five dot com you'll see one...dot com
...you'll see graft windows...that was going to make calls to all those guys and it's going to handle all of the
offices for me the only other asf code that...the right is in these routes I tell that
...I actually want to require ad login.
So, I'm assuming require ad login on this home route and that's going to force people to login if they have
...already logged in I've got my offs code actually done I won't have to write any more often
which is kind of amazing to meand, then I'm just going to write...a little bit of rusk code some to create a factory
...angular factories or how you do factories...services or...other things...how you do most of your service
...you can see I'm just using the angular
dollar http thing to do a quick get request on all of these me such events
...messages me such files me slash notes
...notebooks and me slash member of to get all those things from simple rest
...json so there's no like parsing the response it's just already javascript object so
it's really simple and straightforward and the last thing I have to do is actually call those things in my
controller ...put the controller body in there you see I'm just putting some loading text in
their to start with and then I'm calling all of those endpoints
in the factories and inside of a promise I'm setting them on to the scope which
angular is your model basically so it save...and I go
back here and I had a five on a actually...run the...tools so you can see things one second?
So, I hit save and I
...five you can see that actually is making all of those requests
directly in the browser you can see they're not coming from a server-side
peace or not I didn't do any,
you know, off code in handling access token on that was just
handle because that plug-in knows I registered all those endpoints and it knows to go
give-me access tokens for each one of those endpoints when I don't have oneand, then it will go on automatically
attach them on every...should be request so pretty slick I've integrated with all those different office
...sixty-five api as you can see my calendar events my messages my wonder for business files by
one...and my groups the most important one notebook...food and,
then you can see that they're all coming from if you look at the network trace and chrome you can see that
...all coming directly from the browser using a
course requests so pretty slick simple and easy again that's just with...
libraries I'm just using a library tool for often I'm using whatever framework I'd like for everything else.
Ok, so, then the last thing I want to show you is a
hey we also have a bunch of tools that are specific to the office three sixty-five api is not just for
off and, we have them for a variety of platforms againthey're pretty much all open-source on
office...organization we have...case for ios we have...sdk for android
...an add-in for android studio where you can automatically register for a new
...id from within android studio...your project
...so for java server and...and we have cordoba plugins nowand, we have
...sdk and a bunch of tools for visual studio the tools for visual studio really the coolest
piece all just show you those real quick just give you the kind of tip of the iceberg on that
...go to visual studio I'll show you the file new project creation...so if I go to
file new project and I choose sp net web application this is in the rc of
...visual seo twenty fifteen by the way if I had okay there.
And, I choose nbc you see there's a dialogue here that
...me pick the authentication and adjective directories actually integrated directly in the
founding projects if I choose work in school as my authentication provider
...then choose directly from here...a single tenet app
or multichannel app I can choose which domain which directory I want to put into if I have
multiple I can decide whether or not I want to read directory data in addition to just getting the stuff that's in the open
...connect token...and I can hit okay and when I hit okay it will actually go
...create a project and behind-the-scenes
...go out adjective directory create a new application for me go and get the client id going
...the secret gone register for all those permissions and just in the interest of time I've got a project
...did that really nothing else you look...web configure can see here's
my client id here's my clients secret here's my domain here's
...id all that stuff is configured for me automatically without me having to write a single line of
code if I had a five I have an app that autumn...is already running it'll run on local host
and it will sign the user in a and ask them for permission to access their profile without me writing a
single line of code so, it's pretty slick you just a second here load?
And, then also ...I mention this really quickly just in the interest of time.
This guy...
One I is express running a time.
So, we'll see if I actually looking a project...this
records loading if I look at the project you can see now so it's
...in assign...with this user.
Well, that goes back and loads a page I can show you things like if I go into the
controller you can see there's already user profile
...that's using all of this can fig in order to go on create and as
...active directory clients here's...active directory client and
its making your query for the user a and getting back all of
their basic information like their name and their first and last name I think in this case
in the user profile name but...can get other things like the department or their manager
this is just for the boiler plate code that starting with us if I go to this page
I click on this I'll go to the user profile controller you'll see that it's already able to call as
...active directory and pullback information like my displaying the last thing I'll show you real quick in this
tool is that that's all the single sign on piece so
...you want to single sign on that founding project thing we'll get you but,
we also support the ability to go...click on a project and add
a connected service and this works in almost all project types in
visual studio by the way so even if you're creating like a command-line app and you want to do single sign on and connect office
three sixty-five services you can write click an added...service and choose the office
three sixty-five api is there you can sign in with...that you'd like to develop with source
...more time.
They promised me that by
...tm it's going to use the key chains you want to sign in so many times.
And, it will automatically make sure that I'm registered inside the directory you can see in this case the project was
already registered switches using the same one...set whether it's singular multiple tenants can
...my redirect...my reply urls...and I can request permissions to specific api
...so say I want to request permission to read and write your files and I had apply when I hit
ad will actually go and find all the new get packages for all the sdk is that I need
for whatever I picked so if I chose files or outlook or whatever else will go find
those new get packages in those new get packages only...add them to my projectso,
I can immediately start writing...called a files api and everything's configure formula back
...I don't have to go separately the...management portal ok so that's the that's the quick summary
of what's in visual studio obviously those are the most complete tools I can do a ton that are just point-and-click and
...have to go back and forth between portals I'm...go back to powerpoint
and finish up think of like thirty...the demo visual studio and
summary of a bring obviously sixty-five into your
app what do single sign on start there but then to get the next steps
...in the intelligence that you get from interacting with things like
...calendar from things like the office...with their
...using the office we sixty-five rest api and all the tools and
the sdk is that make it really easy to integrated into your platform there are
...related sessions in fact there's almost a related session for every different
service that I talked about and that's in the office we sixty-five and almost one for
every different platform there's a specific session on integrating office we sixty-five into windows ten apps and
one on integrating office we sixty-five into a zebra naps and motivates development apps
and web apps so take a look at those sessions if you want details on those specific platforms
...do into a ton of detail if there any...already...you-can attend will be online so
read those...a bunch of resources there you probably already heard about this but we're launching a
developer program for office developers that includes a bunch of extra benefits in particular
I'd point out the free developer subscription for a year if you want to go sign up for that thing there's a bunch of
extra benefits around you get free access like a free professional license for a
teller css can...controls and a bunch of other cool stuffso, sign up for that program
will send you newsletters about new releases a new features that are coming out you'll get free access and training all that
kind of stuff that's part of the called action and I hear they're actually some really cool
...down at the office three sixty five developer of
for booth on the first-floor and if you go and get some stickers for
answering some questions I believe you get your own office three sixty-five
...which I'm very jealous of at this point apparently you don't get any of the cool stuff like devices or
...when you actually work for microsoft's
cetera but okay thanks-very-much guys are really appreciates meantime I
...a really busy fast session I hope you took a lot away and opie understand
...much more deeply the office...sixty by rest api...please, please,
please do take the time send-me some feedback communal valuation let-me know what I can do better next time
let-me know what was useful for you I hope you have a great...your build conference thanks-very-much.